Time Warner Audiobooks presents
Rich Dad, Poor Dad
Written by Robert Kiyosaki with Sharon L. Lecter, CPA
And read by Stephen Hoy
Featuring an introduction by Robert Kiyosaki
I had two fathers, a rich one and a poor one.
One was highly educated and intelligent.
He had a Ph.D. and completed four years of undergraduate work in less than two years.
The other father never finished the eighth grade.
Both men were successful in their careers, working hard all their lives.
Both earned substantial incomes.
Yet one struggled financially all his life.
The other would become one of the richest men in Hawaii. One died leaving tens of millions
of dollars to his family, charities, and his church. The other left bills to be paid. Both men
were strong, charismatic, and influential. Both men offered me advice, but they did not advise the same things.
Both men believed strongly in education, but did not recommend the same course of study.
If I had had only one dad, I would have had to accept or reject his advice.
Having two dads advising me offered me the choice of contrasting points of view, one of a rich man and one of a poor man.
Instead of simply accepting or rejecting one or the other, I found myself thinking more,
comparing, and then choosing for myself. The problem was, the rich man was not rich yet,
and the poor man not yet poor. Both were just starting out on their careers,
and both were struggling with money and families.
But they had very different points of view about the subject of money.
For example, one dad would say,
the love of money is the root of all evil.
The other, the lack of money is the root of all evil.
As a young boy, having two strong fathers, both influencing me, was difficult.
I wanted to be a good son and listen, but the two fathers did not say the same things.
The contrast in their points of view, particularly where money was concerned,
was so extreme that I grew curious and intrigued.
I began to start thinking for long periods of time about what each was saying.
Much of my private time was spent reflecting,
asking myself questions such as,
Why does he say that?
and then asking the same question of the other dad's statement.
It would have been much easier to simply say,
Yeah, he's right. I agree with that.
Or to simply reject the point of view by saying, the old man doesn't know what he's talking about. Instead, having two dads whom I
love force me to think and ultimately choose a way of thinking for myself. As a process,
choosing to think for myself turned out to be much more valuable in the long run,
rather than simply accepting or rejecting a single point of view.
One of the reasons the rich get richer, the poor get poorer,
and the middle class struggles in debt
is because the subject of money is taught at home, not in school.
Most of us learn about money from our parents.
So what can a poor parent tell their child about money?
They simply say,
stay in school and study hard. The child may graduate with excellent grades, but with a poor
person's financial programming and mindset. It was learned while the child was young.
Money is not taught in schools. Schools focus on scholastic and professional skills,
but not financial skills. This explains how smart bankers, doctorsastic and professional skills, but not financial skills.
This explains how smart bankers, doctors, and accountants,
who are in excellent grades in school, may still struggle financially all their lives.
Our staggering national debt is due in large part to highly educated politicians and government officials making financial decisions
with little or no training on the
subject of money. I often look ahead to the new millennium and wonder what will happen when we
have millions of people who will need financial and medical assistance. They will be dependent
upon their families or the government for financial support. What will happen when Medicare
and Social Security run out of money? How will a nation survive if teaching children about money
continues to be left to parents, most of whom will be, or already are, poor? Because I had two
influential fathers, I learned from both of them. I had to think about each dad's advice, and in
doing so, I gained valuable insight into the power and effect of one's thoughts on one's life.
For example, one dad had a habit of saying,
I can't afford it.
The other dad forbade those words to be used.
He insisted I say, how can I afford it?
One is a statement and the other is a question.
One lets you off the hook and the other forces you to think.
My seem-to-be-rich dad would explain that by automatically saying the words,
I can't afford it, your brain stops working.
By asking the question, how can I afford it, your brain is put to work.
He did not mean buy everything you wanted.
He was fanatical about exercising your mind, the most powerful computer in the world.
My brain gets stronger every day because I exercise it.
The stronger it gets, the more money I can make.
He believed that automatically saying,
I can't afford it, was a sign of mental laziness.
Although both dads worked hard,
I noticed that one dad had a habit of putting his brain to sleep
when it came to money matters, and the other had a habit of putting his brain to sleep when it came to money matters,
and the other had a habit of exercising his brain.
The long-term result was that one dad grew stronger financially and the other grew weaker.
It is not much different from a person who goes to the gym to exercise on a regular basis
versus someone who sits on the couch watching television.
Proper physical exercise increases
your chances for health, and proper mental exercise increases your chances for wealth.
Laziness decreases both health and wealth. My two dads had opposing attitudes and thought.
One dad thought that the rich should pay more in taxes and take care of those less fortunate. The other said, taxes punish those who produce and reward those who don't produce.
One dad recommended, study hard so you can find a good company to work for.
The other recommended, study hard so you can find a good company to buy.
One dad said, the reason I'm not rich is because I have you kids.
The other said,
The reason I must be rich is because I have you kids.
One dad encouraged talking about money and business at the dinner table.
The other forbade the subject of money to be discussed over a meal.
One said,
When it comes to money, play it safe and don't take risks.
The other said, Learn to manage risk. One said, when it comes to money, play it safe and don't take risks. The other said, learn to manage risk.
One believed, our home is our largest investment and our greatest asset.
The other believed, my house is a liability,
and if your house is your largest investment, you're in trouble.
Both dads paid their bills on time,
yet one paid his bills first while the other paid his bills last.
Being a product of two strong dads allowed me the luxury of observing the effects different thoughts have on one's life.
I noticed that people really do shape their life through their thoughts.
For example, my poor dad always said, I'll never be rich. And that prophecy became reality.
My rich dad, on the other hand, always referred to himself as rich. He would say things like,
I'm a rich man, and rich people don't do this. Even when he was flat broke, after a major
financial setback, he continued to refer to himself as a rich man. He would cover himself by saying,
there is a difference between being poor and being broke. Broke is temporary and poor is eternal.
My poor dad would also say, I'm not interested in money or money doesn't matter. My rich dad
always said, money is power. The power of our thoughts may never be measured or appreciated,
but it became obvious to me as a young boy to be aware of my thoughts and how I expressed myself.
I noticed that my poor dad was poor not because of the amount of money he earned,
which was significant, but because of his thoughts and his actions.
As a young boy, having two fathers,
I became acutely aware of
being careful which thoughts I chose to adopt as my own. Whom should I listen to? My rich dad
or my poor dad? Although both men had tremendous respect for education and learning, they disagreed
in what they thought was important to learn. One wanted me to study hard, earn a degree, and get a good
job to work for money. He wanted me to study to become a professional, an attorney, or an
accountant, or to go to business school for my MBA. The other encouraged me to study to be rich,
to understand how money works, and learn how to have it work for me. I don't work for money,
were the words he would repeat over and over. Money works
for me. At the age of nine, I decided to listen to and learn from my rich dad about money. In doing
so, I chose not to listen to my poor dad, even though he was the one with all the college degrees.
Once I made up my mind whom to listen to, my education about money began. My rich dad taught me over a period of 30 years, until I was age 39.
He stopped once he realized that I knew and fully understood
what he had been trying to drum into my often thick skull.
Money is one form of power, but what is more powerful is financial education.
Money comes and goes.
But if you have the education about how money works,
you gain power over it and can begin building wealth. The reason positive thinking alone does
not work is because most people went to school and never learned how money works, so they spend
their lives working for money. Because I was only nine years old when I started, the lessons my rich
dad taught me were simple.
And when it was all said and done,
there were only six main lessons repeated over 30 years.
This book is about those six lessons.
Put as simply as possible as my rich dad put forth those lessons to me.
The lessons are not meant to be answers, but guideposts.
Guideposts that will assist you and your
children to grow wealthier, no matter what happens in a world of increasing change and uncertainty.